welcome to the third episode of under
the hood so in back in April 2018 we
released the first version of business
Central in the cloud that was the first
time we had business Central as a true
SAS offering as true SAS service and uh
since then we often got the question how
many users can business Central handle
in the cloud so today in this episode we
are going to answer that question and to
help him with that have Christian with
me hi Christian hello so Christian you
know a little bit about Cloud
Technologies right yes I would say so
yeah so you've been working with the
with these business Central and and the
whole Cloud thing since the very
beginning right since day one of when
window Sasha was still a new thing and
we thought that would be an interesting
technology yeah I was part of that
Journey so very early you y you more
than 10 years ago yeah you started
experimenting with with Asia technology
so it's fair to say you an expert in in
in Cloud Technologies right maybe yes
yeah so today we are going to go really
under the hood you're going to see some
things that you don't normally see with
business Central because um some of the
Machinery that is in the cloud is not
publicly documented but we are going to
talk a little bit about it with
Christian today so let's start with
topology let's start with so how how is
that different from for example on Prim
yeah so on Prim you would maybe
typically have uh the NST installed on
one machine a physical machine and the
database maybe on a separate machine or
maybe on the same machine uh in a simple
setup like this and they would be very
close to each other and you would manage
everything in the cloud we do uh things
differently first of all we Microsoft
host everything and we have uh we use a
Technologies so as you can see in this
picture I've Illustrated cre a very simp
simplistic picture of our topology in
the cloud so that's how it looks like in
the cloud that's how it looks like very
very simplified so but enough to explain
what we're going to talk about okay so
we have a VM cluster technically it's a
virtual machine scale set that has a
number of VMS and all our VMS are
configured in the same way they run the
web server and they run the
NST and we typically have uh well we
have from five VMS and up in such a
cluster and then you have users logging
into to the in the browser and you have
systems that call our apis and when they
call we have a low balance that we
implemented that understands business
Central and sessions and all and and
things like that and it decides which VM
should handle the request and it
forwards the request to the right VM so
it's not always the same NST so to speak
that that the the that handles the
request no so two sessions can be for
the same customer for the same
environment can be handled by two
different BMS when you are when you have
a UI session that is you know that lives
for minutes or hours or more uh it will
stay on the same VM though because we
don't move an existing session from one
VM to another so what happen what
happened when um there are many users on
on on the cluster like this like doing
things at the same time yes so we have
those VMS that we have uh let's say we
have five VMS and uh as more and more
users log into the system or maybe we
have uh job cues running or apis being
called uh over time uh the load will
increase on the virtual machine like say
in the morning people come in the Lo
load is very low but over time the load
increases um so at some point uh we we
say you know this is too much for a
given VM we we are not comfortable with
sending more traffic to the VM so I can
illustrate what happens so our uh Lo
balancer continuously keeps an eye on
these VM so it looks at the CPU load for
example it looks at memory it looks at
other things too but I'm just using CPU
here for illustration purposes so it
will it will always know what the CPU
load is on each VM and then we say we
have set a threshold at 60% and if VM
goes above 60% CPU load we say it's it's
getting starting to become overloaded
even though 60% is far away from 100%
why did we choose 60% there's no rule
for this it's uh based on experience uh
it's low enough that we have a good
reaction time it's far away from 100%
but we also want to of course utilize
the VMS so we don't want to set it too
low either so it's like the compromise
we still have 40% available still have a
lot of of capacity left at this point
okay but when this happens what our low
balance I will say is let's give that VM
a break and not send new sessions to it
so the existing as as I explained before
existing sessions we don't move them
they keep running but any new session
will go to let's say vm1 or vm3 and and
thereby we give vm2 a break and and as
the load as the sessions on this VM
start to finish what they were doing the
load we should expect the load to drop
on the VM below 60% again okay so so
what happens if um if all VMS get busy
like if there's really a lot of activi
everybody's working you know hard doing
a lot of sales order or something and
all VMS get above 60% what what what
happens then yeah it's it happens all
the time I just if that happens uh we
add more VMS as simple as that okay so
we have as many we have like practically
infinite number of VMS the asure cloud
right it is and a normal VM cluster we
always have at least five VMS but it's
very normal that we have 10 or 20 or 30
or 40 VMS in a cluster so yeah it can
scale as needed
and what happens when then when
everybody goes home afterwards and then
with all this VM they do nothing yes so
we have so we might scale out
aggressively at more more VMS very
aggressively we also scale in again uh
we do that you know very slowly so so
but we will slow slowly remove VMS again
so we add more you add VMS faster then
we remove them yes so we want to see H
we have had a very low load on the
cluster as a whole for a long time it's
now safe to remove a VM so we do that
okay okay so I have some illustrations
to to show you how how this works in
sort of in real life to give you a feel
for for how it really works so these are
real life um data these are actual
clusters yes this these are actual
clusters so here we have a cluster with
uh nine VM so each VM is represented by
a color and this is a cluster in the US
and the time was uh 5:35 UTC time so it
means it was very late evening in the US
close to midnight and as we can expect
there's not a lot uh happening that at
time of day in the US so the VMS are not
doing much the turquaz one is doing a
bit of work but the others are not doing
almost anything but it's still about 20%
or something so it's not very it's not a
lot of no work no they they're not doing
much and so if we go one minute uh ahead
we can see that all of a sudden
something's happening something's
happening the blue VM and the orange VM
start to do a lot of work we we cannot
say what type of work it is from this
picture it can be job cues it can be
users logging in in the evening also be
B API calls maybe they have some
integration that runs yeah maybe they
copy some data in the badge thing or
something could be yeah but still we are
at what 50% load on those two VMS if we
go one minute uh further ahead we can
see the load continues to rise but still
below the
60% still fine one minute later we can
see that the blue VM crossed line and as
I explained before at this point the low
balancer will say no more new sessions
on this uh VM is the instead it will
create new VMS on another VM and it
looks like it picked the the purple VM
in this case so does it have to be over
60 for like one second or two second
it's just which one like for a
millisecond are we going to add a VM no
uh no we're not going to add VMS as that
aggressively for for deciding to use
another VM yes it's immediate if we see
it's above 60% we will start to use
another one we have we want to react
very quickly to this so if we go 1
minute further ahead we can see as
expected the blue one starts to drop
again because uh it finished the work
that it was doing and we didn't send new
work to it so it starts to to go down
again yeah but we can also see the
orange one and the purple one they got
cross the line now and the low balance
already reacted and sent traffic now to
the I think I think dark blue and dark
green VMS here and so they are starting
to do some of the work and uh and so it
goes the next minute they they all
dropped and maybe this was it I don't
know what happens after this but maybe
that was just a five minute burst of
activity in the US uh in the evening but
it doesn't matter we don't need to know
we don't need to know yeah so this is
how it works so it kind of it might
hover above 60% for a little while see
goes maybe to 66% at its worst here and
that's fine still plenty to go until we
reach 100 and uh yeah that's how it
works and I also have an illustration
about um how we scale out yeah just to
give you a feel for how that works yeah
let's see that so here we have another
cluster this one has 24 VMS so this in
Sweden this in Sweden yes and we can see
the time is 808 in the morning UTC time
so that would be 9:00 a.m. approximately
in Sweden and if we go one minute
forward we can see all of a sudden I
like some coordinated action in Sweden I
don't know they all start they people
come to work they have that their coffee
and now they probably start working
right yes that's the time they come to
work in Sweden apparently um and they
start to do some work and we can see
some VMS have crossed the line above 60%
and and if we move minutes ahead ahead
we can see yeah it's getting you know
it's getting all the VMS are getting
pretty close to 60% some are above and
some are not uh but you know this the
model works the same way so we can see
see that it hovers around 60% when a VM
goes above uh it the low balancer
redirect some traffic to other VM so
therefore they will all start to hover
around 60% but but what what we can see
here is we are getting close to the
point where we not we're not we need to
add more VMS basically because if they
are all above 60% it's it's too much and
we need to have more VMS and this
happens we have an algorithm and we're
tuning that all the time but in this
case we can see in our Telemetry that at
812 it uh it said enough is enough we
need to have more VMS okay so we all all
all the time looking at the algorithm
and we started with one model and we
fine tuning in all the time to make to
provide the best experience for
customers right yes exactly so at a12 we
say we need three more VMS again the
algorithm which we change from time to
time it in this case it would say three
more VMS is the right number so it
requests from Asia to have three more
VMS how long time did that take yeah we
can see in this case it took 10 minutes
and then 11 minutes before we got the
last two VM so okay after 11 minutes we
have three VMS that are ready now it's
it's okay yeah it's enough because we
still have in a whole cluster with 24
VMS we still have 40% buffer yeah above
the 60% that they so just to be clear
it's not like people are waiting 10
minutes for the work to be done they
still have VMS
uh they are they're a bit busy uh so
they continue working as they don't see
anything in in in this case there were
there were no Pro problems at all
because each VM still had a 40% buffer
so as we know from our from our own
laptops you know that's fine it's fine
no problem right and yeah because we
have this big buffer it's also plenty of
time to to create new VM so we can
handle a sudden burst in in traffic even
even if they are pretty loaded we can
handle a burst okay
so what you're saying basically is that
in in terms of VMS and compute there's
there's no problem we always have
capacity yeah I would say uh we we are
pretty mature in this area and uh yeah
capacity is rarely the source of a
performance problem so how about
database how about the database can that
be also a bottle leg for performance
absolutely it means pretty much the same
picture and I have an illustration of
that too so we monitor our our databases
as well mhm and we monitor CPU load IO
Data IO log IO and other things and if
we see that it gets above a certain
threshold we say that database needs
more capacity and then we give it more
capacity we also have an algorithm there
for yes that that monitor certain
matrics to scale the database as well
and I have an example here of a database
where uh you can see that you know the
database was not doing anything uh until
suddenly it started to do something so
so maybe they had some kind of a bad job
so that's also real world this is real
world yeah um and they you know they run
and then they pause for a minute or two
and then they run again and it goes to
85% perhaps CPU so again it's not like
it's a it's it's suffering right it has
necessary capacity but we're not
comfortable with this situation so we
decide at some point to to add more
capacity to this to this database so
after 30 minutes we see
this is enough is enough we want to add
more capacity and so we do and uh and
the pattern from this for this database
seems to some continue in some form you
can see they do some more rounds of this
pattern yeah two more rounds or
something like that I'm not sure it's
the same thing that's happening but but
it looks like it's it's the same could
be the same because the the CPU load
dropped to approximately half of what it
was before and and we doubl the capacity
of the database continuing doing some
some work on this database it adds up
yeah so um so you're saying there's no
capacity problem with the compute and is
we also because we can scale and uh we
can also scale the database if there's a
lot of activity so how come we hear
reports every now and then that uh our
customers they have you know they think
they experience BC as being slow so how
how come if if we don't have you're
saying we don't you know we have this
practically infinite amount of resources
in the cloud so how come users are
experiencing sometime slow performance
yeah the so the source of a performance
problem can be uh a million things okay
but uh we have some uh things we see all
the time that are sources of these
problems and it has typically has to do
with Al code and the way it uses the
database okay because many many problems
are because of database uh Pro you know
queries so mostly database yeah mostly
code exactly okay yeah and I have an
illustration to to show you uh the
typical problems we see okay so here we
have again the VM clusters that run the
AL code and we have a database um and
the three categories are the first one
is logging database logging which we are
all familiar with so one session takes a
lock on a record for example and another
session another user wants to take the
same lock but they can't so they have to
wait and and while they are waiting you
know the UI uh is slow
uh so that's one source of problems
people stepping on each other's toes so
to speak but that's not a cloud problem
is it no no that's uh just just how
databases work also something we we we
know from the from the on Prem world yes
exactly the other category is long
running queries so this typically
happens when you have a lot of data like
you have a table with many millions of
rows and then maybe you do a search uh
and you're missing an index typically so
you have to read all the rows or the
database has to read all the rows mhm
and that can be slow okay and the last
category is uh many short queries so for
example if you iterate over you have
maybe thousands of sales orders or sales
lines and somehow in your code you have
an iteration over these and for every
iteration you make a database yeah so
even if the database each database call
is just one millisecond if you have
thousands of them it adds up to to
multiple seconds right and so you can Fe
it in the UI so those are the
three sources of performance problems we
see most often so are they are the
patterns which are actually worse in the
cloud than on
Prem uh yeah so you can see all these
patterns uh on Prem as well but uh this
the the third category many short
queries I would say it's probably
typically worse in the cloud and that is
because as I explained in the beginning
on Prem the database and the NST are
practically to yes so the latency there
is zero M but in the cloud with
buildings Data Center buildings far
apart there can be a latency typically
less than a millisecond but it's there
yeah times a million it's becomes
significant so something you wouldn't be
seeing in the in the collocated
environment on Prem becomes actually a
problem in the cloud it can it can
happen yes so yeah so the recommendation
is to to to try to avoid that which will
also help of course on Prem so
it's just a good thing to not do
unnecessary to do that on Prem as well
too so what what um so how can um how
can I troubleshoot these this
performance how can our our developers
troubleshoot these issues this
performance issues so over over time
we've build up a number of tools and and
I want to highlight four tools today and
the first tool is the incline
performance profiler which is my go-to
tool for these kinds of things um then
we have two pages in The in the product
that you can just open the database
locks page and the database missing
indexes page and finally have we have
Telemetry with application insights
where you can also troubleshoot some
performance problems okay we'll put some
links in the in in the comments to for
the documentation of of these of these
tools so yeah yeah yeah so um so let's
start with the uh in in client
performance profile tell us a little
more about it this is this is a tool
which is
um in in the product yep it's in the
product anybody any user can can open it
you don't need to install anything it's
it's just there it's one of the nice
things about it it's it's always there
uh so yeah no no preparation no
installation let's look at it so this is
how it looks I in the lower left hand
corner I've Illustrated how you open it
you go to the help and support page and
then analyze performance and then it
opens up and uh it's very simple to use
so you click Start
then you uh repeat the slow scenario in
this case I tried to post the sales
order it took almost six seconds which
is pretty slow so you turn it on you
turn the profile on and you run your
scenario that that you You observe is
slow and then you press stop okay and
then it gives you the result and in this
case it said it took 6 seconds and it
shows also immediately that it's the
base application that is using all the
time and a few other extensions are also
using a bit of the time and if you want
more details you can toggle
this toggle below and uh you can see for
example which method was using a lot you
get a Tre view for example of the call
Stacks in your code in your Al code and
you can see where the time was spent
pinpoint the exact method where so if I
have if I let's say I have so in your
example it's the B app right but if
let's say I have a um a bunch of
extensions installed on my system and
then I will be able to to see which
extension is giving problem performance
would the first graph here immediately
you will see let's say you installed an
appsource app and it has some bad Al
code you will immediately be able to see
this from this picture so pretty
powerful tool M right I think
so um so you mentioned also um database
lock yes yes so if you if you have a if
you think you have a database a problem
with locks in the database we have this
page in the in the product database
locks page again you can just go and
open it product it's just there yeah in
this case we don't have any locks in the
system but if you have locks it might
look something like this so how it works
is when we open it up we ask
SQL uh what locks are currently being
held in this database and who is waiting
to get a lock right now and if you press
F5 it's going to ask SQL again and say
now the it looks like this so you get a
point time view on locks and waiting for
locks in the database so in this case we
can see n wil has been granted a lock on
a key of the mixer table and he was on
the mixer list page uh and it was the
onaction trigger that did it for example
right this is a an example right and you
can see that deah is currently waiting
for lock so she's probably not happy
right now because she's waiting to get
a lck so now you already know more about
why has to wait so you wear in the col
in that case the trigger you can go in
the trigger and try to uh to optimize
the the Cod take the lock hold the lock
for shorter or maybe avoid it all
together okay okay so um so that that's
was about the Locking and um around the
database there was also something about
indexes and missing indexes so we have
the database missing indexes page and
here I don't have a good example I only
have this example where it's one of our
tables system tables that was missing in
index which we didn't add it so you will
not see that again um so the way this
works is when you run a database in Asia
Asia SQL will monitor your database and
it will do this thought experiments
where it will say what if I add this
index what would that do to Performance
how often is how many queries would it
help how much faster would they
execute the positives but also how
expensive will it be to maintain this
index because it it is not for free to
have an index it has to be it's one more
thing to maintain for the database and
that's something that SQL does by itself
in the background you don't have to do
anything you don't have to turn it on or
anything something that SQL it's a SQL
of it's a feature of SQL right it is a
feature of SQL it just does it in in the
background and what we can do similar to
the database logs is we can query into
SQL and say what recommendations
in terms of indexes do you have and
that's is what you can see in this in
this view so the reason I I don't have a
good example is because you need to
actually run for some days and have a
problem for it to to to make that
conclusion and say I recommend this so
as a partner if you if you have a
customer database I encourage you to go
and look and maybe you will see some
real uh recommendations yeah and when
you actually add that index it usually
makes a a big difference it can it can
make in the world
yeah all right and then uh so that was
that was about the database and finally
you also mention application insights
application insights yes so this is uh
yeah something I recommend all fers to
do is enable application insights on the
environments which they can do in in the
business Central admin
Center um you learn a lot about what's
going what's going on in the service
because as we run whenever something
interesting happens we emit an event to
your application insights application
insights is a is a Microsoft product
which is um not only for BC but a lot of
other products are using it right you
can use it for practically anything yeah
it's it's a very uh popular yeah uh and
a service also MH um and so here we have
an example where we can see that we get
an event that a SQL statement was
executed we can see that it took 4
milliseconds which is not super fast
also
very slow uh and a note here um normally
we would not emit these events when a
SQL query takes less than 750
milliseconds because if we did we would
just overflow the application insides
because this happens many times so how
do I by the way how do I enable
application inside how do I turn it up
yeah so that's that's that's what I have
Illustrated in the lower left corner you
can do that in a UI session today that's
a trick you go and enable additional
logging and for for the duration of this
session it will emit all SQL statements
to your avigation ins so you will see a
lot of of events in your appication
insights but now you can query it so if
you have a suspicion that you are doing
many calls and you're not quite sure
what they are you can enable this and
you can see if this is really the case
and you can sum the durations and see
yeah this is the reason it took 5
Seconds you can also see further details
you can see the ex SQL statement and you
can see where in the code it was
executed so now you are well suited to
maybe go and fix the problem so pretty
much in all the the tools you you
mentioned here we can trace Trace all
the way back trace the problem all the
way back to the code and and and see
where where the problem is yeah so they
these are troubleshooting tools right
they pinpoint the problem they don't
necessarily say how you can solve it you
need to find a solution you have to use
your own skills there yeah yeah
so question um how many users can BC
handle in the cloud so so we don't have
a hard
limit so you can have we have customers
with hundreds or thousands of users um
adding more users it's not really a
problem because we just scale out and
add more capacity except for one area
which is uh locking where the more users
you have yeah that work at the same time
the more likely they are to step on each
other's toes and uh you know one does
something and the other has to wait for
the first thing to finish and uh again
this has a lot to do with how the AL
code is written so yeah if you can
rewrite it in a way that it does less
locking then it will also unlock uh
scalability in terms of more users so I
guess the answer is it depends it
depends it depends a lot but do you have
some examples of what actually the seual
can handle and we also have a a website
now that you can go and look at uh
yourself and I I I took a few examples
from it um so the last example here is
number of users as I mentioned we have
customers with more than thousand of us
more than thousand users many many
customers with more than 100 users so
not a
problem some other examples and there
are more in the in the article so this
article is um or a scalability guide
that we released recently we'll put some
Link in the description so you can take
a look at it and these examples are in
there these examples are in there and
these are examples of of real customers
that did something or have something
like for example the first line 5,000
sales invoices posted in one hour it's a
real example from some customer I don't
know we don't know who it is but we can
see that a customer posted that many
invoices in one hour and there are more
examples here there also examples of how
many API calls you can call which uh
which is quite a lot I think so in most
customers will will find that this is
plenty and that's maybe also one of the
goals with this is to give some uh
confidence to to Partners that they can
bring large customers like if you a
partner and you have a customer that
maybe makes uh needs to post a thousand
sales invoices in an hour maybe you look
at this number and you say that's
probably not going to be a problem
because we have other customers that do
much more than that and so they should
be comfortable to bring that customer to
the cloud but but still if if I'm a
partner and I have I have this this
customer with many many users and I know
they are going to do some um pretty
intensive operation simultaneously on on
BC so I'm a little bit worried about
maybe a particular scenario U it could
be something like I don't know time
registration I know that they they have
some you know load very you know High
Peak High load um um periods where where
there's a lot of activity on the St
where is there anything I can do to get
more confidence
yes so if you if you are concerned uh if
you are bringing a large customer and
you are want to make absolutely sure
that they will run fine from the day one
in the cloud you can test it out so you
can simulate we have a toolkit for that
it's called the performance toolkit and
it is assigned one of the main goals is
to just to do the what if scenario what
if I have a customer that does this many
sales orders with this many users and
whatever scenario they might have you
can simulate it you can simulate it to
say I have 10 users they do 10 sales
orders per hour each uh or whatever the
scenario might be and then you can run
it and uh you can run it in the cloud so
in our service can you run with like a
thousand users if you want yeah in
principle yes yes yeah um and U while it
runs you can also log in yourself right
it's running in an environment just like
any other environment you can log in and
you can see you can use the database
lock space for example yeah the tools
all the tools you mentioned before can
you use to uh troubleshoot the system to
see what locks are being held maybe you
use that to to go and change some code
uh you can see Telemetry you can also
just log in yourself and see how does it
feel what if I also now create a sales
order and post it does it feel fast
while many users are doing the same
thing in the background so you you can
you can boost your confidence for that
customer by by using this performance
toolkit all right thank thank you
Christian welcome I hope you found this
useful again we'll put some links in the
description with all the tools that um
that Christian talked about and also to
the scalability guide thank you for
watching and see you next time